Do Vegans Have Lower Bone
Density and More Fractures?
This video and the next explore
whether there's a difference
in bone density between those
who eat meat and those who don't.
"Bone Density, Fracture Rates,
and Vitamin D in Vegans"
Osteoporosis has become a major
public health problem worldwide.
The morbidity and even mortality
of osteoporotic complications,
such as hip fractures, are severe.
Osteoporosis is diagnosed by testing
low in bone mineral density
and afflicts about 1 in 20 men
over age 65, and 1 in four women.
"Do We Need to Be Concerned
about Bone Mineral Density
in Vegetarians and Vegans? "
There are studies showing
vegetarian-style diets during
adolescence can have a positive
impact on bone in young adulthood,
but what we really want to know is
about osteoporosis at older ages.
In an earlier video, I talked about
a meta-analysis that concluded
that vegetarian diets, particularly
vegan diets, were associated
with lower bone mineral density,
but only by a clinically
insignificant amount.
Given the relationship between fracture
risk and bone mineral density,
the relative risk of fracture in vegans
would only be about 10% higher
than in meat-eaters, but that doesn't
sound very insignificant to me.
Now I talked about how the
differences in bone mineral density
are largely just a function of
vegetarians and particularly vegans
having such low rates of obesity.
Obese individuals are protected
from osteoporosis because
they do so much
weight-bearing exercise
just walking from one room
to the next basically.
But we only care about
bone mineral density
because we care
about bone fractures.
What's the comparative
fracture risk in vegetarians
versus nonvegetarians?
Now we're talking.
Compared with meat eaters,
same risk for vegetarians,
but a 30% higher risk for vegans.
Now it was mostly wrist
and arm fractures;
there weren't any hip fractures.
Wrist fractures are among the most
common fractures, and interestingly
occurs typically in women who
are in good health and active.
It's the kind of fracture you get
if you like trip when you run
and fall on an outstretched hand.
But the 30% increased risk was after
controlling for non-dietary factors
including activity, such as
exercise or an active workplace.
The increased risk only disappeared
when they controlled for calcium.
Vegans only were at higher risk
when they got under 525 mg
of calcium a day, which is equal to
the estimated average requirement.
Among those getting at least 525
there was no greater risk.
So the higher fracture risk in
the vegans appeared to be
a consequence of
inadequate calcium intake,
which is essential
for bone health
regardless of what
kind of diet you eat.
You don't need to drink milk.
A greater intake of milk
and dairy products
is not associated with a lower risk
of osteoporosis or hip fracture.
In fact, every additional cup or so
of cow's milk a day was associated
with a 9% greater risk of hip
fracture in prospective studies.
But you do have to get
calcium from somewhere.
Plant-based sources include
almonds, sesame seeds, tofu,
calcium-fortified plant milks,
or the best sources:
dark green leafy vegetables
such as kale ---
basically any dark green leafies,
except for spinach, beet greens,
or chard, which are just
stingy with their calcium.
And most vegans in the study
were getting more than the 525.
There's lots of healthy foods
packed with calcium,
but they only work if
you actually eat them.
But wait.
What about the mountain of data
showing that dietary calcium intake
is not associated with risk
of fractures, and there's
no evidence that increasing calcium
intake prevents fractures,
and so increasing calcium intake
should not be recommended
for fracture prevention.
But that's based on giving
extra calcium to people
who are already getting
enough calcium.
So it might just be like
a plateau effect.
Take women getting only 500 mg of
calcium a day and randomize them
to calcium supplements,
and you can drop hip fracture
rates 40% within 18 months.
Now they also gave them vitamin D,
and the women did start out
seriously deficient with vitamin D
levels down around 15,
so it's hard to tease out the
effects of calcium versus the D.
But vegans who aren't supplementing
with D at higher latitudes
can dip down that low
during the winter months, too.
Now there was a study in Shanghai
that found comparable bone health,
despite lower D levels
down around 15.
They were also low
in calcium intake
and still had similar
bone mineral density,
but given that fracture study,
I'd recommend people make sure
they're getting enough calcium
and enough vitamin D.
But that fracture study
was published in 2007.
A 2020 update found
a higher risk of fractures,
even in vegans getting more
than 700 mg of calcium a day.
What explains that?
We'll explore just that question next.
As I noted in my video on
bone mineral density,
vegetarians had slightly lower bone
mineral density in their spines.
Although the difference was
basically within the margin of error
for the test, if the bone quality
really is compromised, it could
lead to collapsed vertebrae,
increased spinal fracture risk,
but there's no evidence for this.
The incidence of vertebral fracture
was ascertained in older women
who had been vegan for most of
their lives -- 34 years on average.
And despite their calcium intake
being terrible, about half that
of the nonvegans, and a quarter
of them vitamin D deficient,
the incidence of vertebral fractures
was not significantly different.
Although the vegans had a higher
prevalence of vitamin D deficiency
and lower dietary calcium
intakes, the two factors
were not associated
with bone loss.
In fact, the annual loss in bone
mineral density in the hips
of vegans was less than
half that of the meat eaters,
though the difference did not
reach statistical significance.
Vegetarian women had not been
found to be at higher risk
of any kind of fractures including
wrist fractures in this case,
though among vegetarians,
those who consumed the least
vegetable protein intake were
at the highest risk for fracture.
Those who ate beans every day,
or nuts, or like veggie burgers
only had a third of the wrist fractures
compared to vegetarians
who only ate beans or
other higher protein foods
less than three times a week.
So those that consume a vegan
or vegetarian diet may be
at increased risk of fracture unless
care is taken to ensure an adequate
quantity and variety of foods high
in protein, such as whole grains,
nuts, and beans, split peas,
chickpeas, or lentils are in the diet.
That's one of the reasons
in my free Daily Dozen app
I recommend whole grains
and legumes every day.
Hip fractures are even more
serious. Those eating legumes,
like beans every day, reduced
their risk of hip fracture
by more than 60%, compared to
40% lower risk from meat protein,
with plant-based meats
coming in in between
with about 50% lower
risk of hip fractures.
What's the bottom line
on plant-based diets and
bone health according
to this 2020 review?
Theoretically, a long-term
plant-based diet may reduce
the risk of osteoporosis, but
that has yet to be demonstrated.
What we do know is that
plant-based diets, when ensuring
adequate calcium and vitamin D levels,
don't appear to have any
detrimental effects on bone health.
But this was published August 2020.
In November 2020, the 12-year
follow-up to the study I talked about
in my last video on comparative
fracture risk in vegetarians
versus nonvegetarians
was published, finding that
non-meat eaters, especially vegans,
had higher risks of
total bone fractures,
including at sites associated with
osteoporosis such as hip fractures.
It comes out to be about 20 more
cases in vegans for every 1000
people over 10 years.
So if indeed this is cause-and-effect,
eating vegan there would be
an annual 1 in 500 chance
of having a bone fracture
that you otherwise
might not have had.
Was it because they weren't
eating enough beans?
Apparently not, since
vegans getting more protein
still apparently had higher risk.
Maybe it was because they
weren't getting enough calcium?
Apparently not, since vegans
getting more calcium
still apparently had higher risk.
What about bone and vitamin B12?
If you remember EPIC-Oxford,
where the bone data comes from,
is the same group of British vegans
who had rampant B12 deficiency.
More than half the vegans were
B12 deficient because they
weren't adequately supplementing
with B12 or B12-fortified foods.
This can lead to high
homocysteine levels,
which not only increase stroke risk,
but may increase the
activity of bone-eating cells.
This was in a petri dish, but you do
indeed see low bone mineral density
in those born with a birth defect
that leads to high homocysteine
levels in the blood. Therefore,
high serum homocysteine
may be regarded as a factor
that can reduce both
bone mass and quality,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
And homocysteine-lowering
treatment failed to reduce
the risk of bone fracture.
So in the end, the effect of B12
deficiency in bone health
remains to be established.
OK, so how do we explain the higher
fracture rates found among vegans?
The investigators conclude that their
findings suggest that bone health
in vegans requires further research,
but there were some clues.
The elevated fracture risk,
both for total fractures
and for hip fractures specifically,
was only significant for
those under a BMI of 22.5,
which is like under about 130 pounds
for a woman of average height.
So part of the problem is that vegans
tend to be so slender on average.
Why are overweight and obese
individuals protected from fractures?
Well, think about it. They have
cushioning during a fall.
There's more of a
cushion on your hips.
Also, there's an enzyme in fatty
tissue that churns out estrogen,
which is why women increase
their breast cancer risk
a percentage point for every
pound they gain in adulthood.
But estrogen can also have
a bone-preserving effect.
Now you can get the best of both
worlds consuming soy foods,
preventing bone loss while
at the same time associated
with lessening breast
cancer risk for both estrogen
receptor positive tumors and
estrogen receptor negative tumors.
Finally, overweight and obese
individuals may also have
stronger bones just from
the increased weight-bearing.
Carrying 100 extra pounds,
you're doing major
weight bearing exercise
just walking across the room.
So the risk difference they saw
between vegans and meat eaters
were likely at least partially
due to the difference in BMI.
My money, however,
is on vitamin D.
Great Britain is at
Canadian latitudes.
The sun's rays are
at such an angle
during the winter months up there
that the vitamin D levels among
British vegans in the wintertime
drops down to suboptimal levels.
Ideally, we should be up around
75 nanomoles per liter,
or 30 nanograms per milliliter
depending on what units you're using,
which the vegans nail in the summer.
It is the sunshine vitamin after all.
But in the winter, not getting
the vitamin D added to dairy or
found naturally in oily fish, if vegans
aren't supplementing at that latitude
during the winter, their vitamin
D levels may drop too low.
Now randomized controlled trials
show that vitamin D alone
does not seem to
reduce fracture rates,
but boosting people's D and
calcium at the same time does.
So maybe it was a combination of the
relatively low D and calcium intakes
among the vegans that led
to their higher fracture rates.
We won't know for sure
until it's actually put to the test,
and when it is you can be sure
I'll do a video about it.